Oliver Doepner

Halifax, Nova Scotia oliver.doepner [at] gmail.com http://oliver.doepner.net/

IT Skills

- Programming languages:
 Expert level: Java, bash
- Web Technologies:
 HTML5, CSS3, XML/XSL,
 JQuery, Servlets, JSF,
 Spring Web Flow, GWT,
 SVG, Unicode / i18n
- Java Technologies:

 Java 6/7/8, JEE, Spring,
 Hibernate, JDBC, JMS,
 Java Mail, Swing, Web
 Services, JAXB, JAXWS,
 Ehcache, Log4J
- Software Engineering:
 OOP / OOD, UML, Design
 Patterns, MVC, Refactoring,
 Test-Driven Development,
 Extreme Programming (XP),
 Agile / Iterative methods
- Project Management : Confluence, JIRA, Bugzilla, Aegis, OTRS, JSPWiki, MediaWiki
- Development Tools: IntelliJ, Eclipse, Netbeans, Vim, Maven, Ant, Git, SVN, CVS, Perforce, Teamcity, Hudson/Jenkins, Bamboo, JUnit, HtmlUnit, Selenium
- Servers / Databases:
 Glassfish, Weblogic, JBoss,
 Tomcat, Jetty, Oracle,
 Postgres, MySQL, MariaDB,
 Apache Derby
- Operating Systems:
 Debian GNU/Linux, Ubuntu
 OpenSolaris, MacOS X,
 Windows, Cygwin

Professional Profile

I am a Software Engineer and IT professional with a focus on object oriented development and design, preferrably using Java and Open Source components.

My <u>IT skills</u> are based on 20+ years of hands-on programming experience, <u>professional software development</u> since 1995 and a broad <u>academic background</u>.

I help teams to achieve quality results and customer satisfaction through practices like intention-driven development, continuous integration, frequent code reviews and controlled refactoring.

I have <u>developed applications</u> in domains like aerospace, internet services, oil & gas, steel, postal services, finance, government and small businesses.

Education and Studies

University of the Saarland, Germany

1998-2002 State examination in <u>Mathematics</u> and <u>German</u> 1995-1998 Intermediate Diploma in Computational Linguistics

IBM Scientific Centre, Heidelberg, Germany

Summer 1996 Research project in Computer Assisted Language Learning (CALL)

University of Sussex, United Kingdom

1994-1995 ERASMUS scholar, Certificate in Maths & Informatics

Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany

1991-1994 Intermediate Diploma in <u>Maths</u> and <u>Informatics</u> 1991-1993 Intermediate Examination in History

Claus-von-Stauffenberg Schule, Germany

until 1990 High School Diploma, highest GPA of the school year

Work experience

IMP Solutions, Halifax, Nova Scotia

2015-now Software Developer: Helicopter Maintenance, Java, GWT, Hibernate

CGI. Halifax. Nova Scotia

2008-2015 Senior Consultant / Software Engineer: Enterprise Java systems

SupportSoft, Halifax, Nova Scotia

2007-2008 Software Engineer: J2EE, JMS, Caching, Web Services, Unit testing

iKu Systemhaus AG, Saarbrücken

2002-2004, Software Engineer: Swing and Web client/server applications, email 2005-2006 security solutions, all stages of the software development life cycle

University of the Saarland, Maths Teaching Library

1999-2001 Library Assistant, Linux admin, Java developer, online catalog search

i2c Systems, Bad Homburg

2000 Requirements and Design for multi-language J2EE applications

DFKI Saarbrücken, Language Technology Lab

1995-1996 R&D assistant: Semantic data extraction, Web development

KfW Bankengruppe, Frankfurt/Main

1995-1999 Software Developer: Object-oriented user interfaces, Oracle DB, C++

Desktop Display Ltd., Brighton, UK

1995 Internship as web developer using NCSA webserver

Software Projects

In all of these projects I worked as principal / core developer or team lead:

IMP Solutions – FMAS: The Fleet Management and Analytics System is the integrated software suite supporting the maintenance of all Canadian Search and Rescue helicopters.

[Java 7, Hibernate, Lucene, GWT, MariaDB, Tomcat, Intellij, SVN, Maven, Linux, Atlassian tools]

CGI - Capital Markets: As a senior software engineer I worked for a large international investment bank on advanced Java features of complex systems and provided technical guidance to our developer teams in business domains like Clearing, Risk Management and Fixed Income.

[Java 7, JPA, Spring, Oracle, Coherence, Tibco, JMS, JGroups, Intellij, Maven, Jenkins, Nexus, Linux]

CGI - Oil & Gas AMS: I was the Senior Software Engineer for our service delivery to a major Canadian oil & gas company, maintaining 150+ Java based web applications, with a team of 5 - 10 Java Developers.

[Java 6, Tomcat 6, IntelliJ, Struts, JSP, GWT, Spring, Hibernate, iBatis, Ant, RMI, Confluence, JIRA, Bamboo]

CGI - Wealth Core Platform: During one of the biggest software projects at CGI, I served as Technical Lead for the UI layer, building a custom framework, coordinating about 10 developers across four CGI locations.

[Java 6, Spring Web Flow, JSF 1.2 / Facelets, Tomcat 6, Spring, JAXB, JUnit, Eclipse, Maven, Hudson/Jenkins, SVN]

CGI - Canada Post - BDT: Business tool that prints all paperwork and automates the shipping process.

[Java 5, Spring, XML/XSL, XSL-FO, Apache FOP, TestNG, PdfBox, Weblogic, IntelliJ IDEA, Maven, SVN]

SupportSoft - ServiceGateway: Remote management of home network devices using TR-069

[J2EE, Weblogic, JBoss, EJB, JMS, Web Services (XFire), EhCache, Oracle 10g, Perforce, Adobe Flex]

iKu - SPONTS: A Java based SMTP, POP3 and IMAP proxy that provides mailserver security features.

[Java, SMTP/S, POP3/S, IMAP/S, Apache Tomcat, Hibernate, Apache Derby, I18n, Embedded Linux]

iKu - LI Inspektor: Lawful Interception (LI) testing tool for the German Federal Network Agency [Java, JSF/MyFaces, Hibernate, JavaMail, Apache FTP, POP3/S, IMAP/S, SMTP/S]

iKu - Bodward: An email monitoring store that plugs into Lawful Interception solutions

[Java, Apache FTP API, Java RMI, TCP networking, Hibernate, Apache Derby, dom4j]

iKu - emVisu: Visualizes heavy plate temperatures for the steel manufacturer Dillinger Hütte GTS [Java Swing, Custom Swing Widgets / LayoutManager, RMI, JMS, JDBC, MySQL]

iKu - AutoCool: Cooling plans visualization and process control for Dillinger Hütte GTS

[Java Swing, Input Validation Framework, DAO Pattern, JDBC, MySQL]

iKu - HSA Control: Steel plate branding machine control UI for Dillinger Hütte GTS.

[Java Swing, JMS, RMI, Custom Datagram Protocol, C struct parsing]

iKu - Plakatdrucker: A webshop for customizable print products

 $[Apache\ Tomcat,\ JSP\ Custom\ Tags,\ CSS,\ Apache\ File Upload,\ Java Mail,\ JDBC\]$

iKu - IceWorld: Monitoring and configuration tool for the N-TEC Icebox RAID system

[Java, Tomcat, JSP Custom Tags, CSS, RXTX/Comm, RMI, Java Swing, Swing DnD]

iKu - CashTrend: Calculation and generation of financial OpenOffice documents based on customer data [Java Swing, OpenOffice Java API, JDBC, MySQL]

MdBib: Online Public Access Catalogue (OPAC) for a library of at the University of the Saarland.

[Apache Tomcat, Apache Jserv, Java Servlets, MySQL]

KfW - Infrastruktur: Migration of the mainframe based IT of KfW Bankengruppe to a client/server infrastructure.

[OOD/OOP, Gupta/Centura, Win32 API, C++, IBM RS/6000, IBM IMS, Oracle DB]